Guide to the Alexander Blackburn Papers, 1880-1999 RL.00114
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Alexander Blackburn papers
1880-2020
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Blackburn, Alexander
RL.00114
26.5 Linear Feet
Professor emeritus of English and Creative Writing at the University of Colorado at Colorado Springs; novelist; son of Duke University faculty member William M. Blackburn. Writings and correspondence of Alexander Blackburn, including books, correspondence, drafts, and typescripts of unpublished works. Also includes Blackburn and Cheney family history materials, photographs, and a scrapbook.
Access Restrictions
Access note. Collection contains fragile audiovisual/photographic formats that may need to be reformatted before use. Contact Research Services for access.
Provenance
The Alexander Blackburn Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1999, 2004, and 2020.
Biographical Note
Alexander Blackburn (b. 1929) is the son of William Blackburn and Elizabeth Cheney Bayne Blackburn. He is a graduate of the University of North Carolina (M.A., 1956) and the University of Cambridge (Ph.D., 1963). He served in the U. S. Army during the Korean War before becoming a professor of English and literature at the University of Colorado at Colorado Springs in 1973. His interests and writings center on the American West; he has also published a critical study on the writer-philosopher Frank Waters. Blackburn also founded and edited the Writers' Forum literary journal. He retired 1995 but continues to write and publish. His books and novels include the following:
A Strange Joy
Remembering Time: Stories and Novellas
Creative Spirit: Toward a Better World
A Sunrise Brighter Still: The Visionary Novels of Frank Waters
The Cold War of Kitty Pentecost
The Myth of the Picaro: Continuity and Transformation of the Picaresque Novel, 1554-1954
More information on Alexander Blackburn can be found at his website, www.alexanderblackburn.com. His autobiography, Meeting the Professor (2008), details both his life and that of his father, William Blackburn.
Collection Overview
Collection contains two accessions. Accession (1999-0184) (1102 items; 6.0 lin. ft.; dated 1953-1998), consists primarily of writings by Alexander Blackburn, including books, articles, clippings, and typescripts of unpublished works. Also included are correspondence with writer Frank Waters and some other letters; memorabilia; and editorial files and an almost complete run of the literary journal, Writer's Forum, which Blackburn edited.
Accession (2010-0012) (6750 items; 9 lin. ft.; dated 1880-1990s) and accession (2020-0099; 11.5 lin. ft) includes writings, drafts, books, and family history materials. Included are materials from Alexander Blackburn's mother, Elizabeth Cheney Blackburn, and the Cheney family.
Related Material
Related collections include the William Blackburn Papers, 1859-1985 and undated.
Memorabilia; Authors, American -- 20th century -- Correspondence; American fiction -- 20th century; Clippings (information artifacts); Blackburn, Elizabeth Cheney; Waters, Frank, 1902-1995; Blackburn, Alexander
- Accession (1999-0184), 4 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Accession (1999-0184) (dated 1953-1998) consists primarily of writings by Alexander Blackburn, including books, articles, clippings, and typescripts of unpublished works. Also included is correspondence with writer Frank Waters and some other letters; memorabilia; and editorial files and an almost complete run of the literary journal, Writer's Forum, which Blackburn edited.
  - Personal Papers (Box 1)
    - Dossier to 1994, letters, commentaries on books together with some clippings about, Suddenly a Mortal Splendor. (1 binder) (Box 1)
    - Phillips Academy Andover Class of 1947 50th Reunion Book (1997). (Box 1)
    - Dictionary of Literary Biography Yearbook: 1985 (Box 1)
    - Faculty Book Award, University of Colorado, Colorado Springs, 1993 (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - Chancellor's Award, 1994 (1 folder) (Box 1)
    - Letter to Prof. Maurice Cramer about The Cold War of Kitty Pentecost (Box 1)
    - Frank Waters Correspondence, photos, etc. (1 black binder) (Box 1)
  - Writers' Forum, Editorial files (4 tapes) See also Box 4 (Box 1)
  - Writings (Box 2)
    - The Beams of Love. A Novel, Typescript, 1998 (Box 2)
    - Creative Spirit: Essays on Literature, Imagination, and the New World of Consciousness, Typescript, 1998 (Box 2)
  - Publications
    - The Myth of the Picaro: Continuity and Transformation of the Picaresque Novel, 1554-1994 First edition. Cloth (Box 2)
    - The Cold War of Kitty Pentecost. First edition. Cloth. (Box 2)
    - Suddenly a Mortal Splendor. First edition. Cloth. (Box 2)
    - Higher Elevations: Stories from the West, & 'Writers' Forum' Anthology First edition. Cloth (Box 2)
    - A Sunrise Brighter Still: The Vision Novels of Frank Waters. First edition. Cloth. (Box 2)
    - A Sunrise Brighter Still: The Visionary Novels of Frank Waters. Limited edition. Leather spine-autographed by Frank Waters and Tal Luther. (Box 2)
    - The Interior Country: Stories of the Modern West. First edition. Cloth. (Box 2)
    - The Interior Country: Stories of the Modern West. First edition. Paper. (Box 2)
    - Flaubert and the Realism of Henry James" M.A. thesis, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill. Bound typescript. (Box 2)
    - The Picaresque Novel: A Literary Idea, 1554-1954. Ph. D. dissertation, University of Cambridge. Bound typescript. (Box 2)
    - Faulkner and the Southern Renaissance. First edition, Cloth. Contains an essay by A. B. (Box 2)
    - Conflict and Arms Control. First edition, Cloth. Contains an essay by A. B (Box 2)
    - American Vanguard 1956. First edition. Cloth. Missing dust jacket. Contains A. B.'s first published story. (Box 2)
    - Dictionary of Literacy Themes and Motifs. 2 vols. First edition. Cloth Vol. 2 contains an essay by A. B. (Box 3)
    - Sundays in Tutt Library with Frank Waters. First edition. Paper. Contains an essay by A. B. (Box 3)
    - Frank Waters: Man and Mystic. First edition. Cloth. Contains an essay by A. B. (Box 3)
    - Writers' Forum Volumes
      1 and 3 are missing. The bound copy of Vol. 5 is damaged, but an unbound complete text is attached. Vol. 11, the Frank Waters Issue, is an extremely rare book. Vol. 17, with Index to Vols. 1-16, has some cover damage. Vol. 22 was edited by A.B.'s successor, C. Kenneth Pellow
      - Volume. 2 (1975) (Box 3)
      - Volume 4 (1977) (Box 3)
      - Volume 5 (1978) (Box 3)
      - Volume 6 (1979) (Box 3)
      - Volume 7 (1981) (Box 3)
      - Volume 8 (1982) (Box 3)
      - Volume 8 (1982) (Box 3)
      - Volume 9 (1983) (Box 3)
      - Volume 10 (1984) (Box 3)
      - Volume 11 (1985) (Box 3)
      - Volume 12 (1986) (Box 3)
      - Volume 13 (1987) (Box 3)
      - Volume 14 (1988) (Box 3)
      - Volume 15 (1989) (Box 3)
      - Volume 16 (1990) (Box 3)
      - Volume 17 (1991) (Box 3)
      - Volume 18 (1992) (Box 3)
      - Volume 19 (1993) (Box 3)
      - Volume 20 (1994) (Box 3)
      - Volume 21 (1995) (Box 3)
      - Volume 22 (1996) (Box 3)
    - Studies in Frank Waters. Edited by Charles Adams. (Box 3)
      Vol. 5 (1982) through Vol. 19 (1997), missing Vol. 17 (1995). A.B. frequently wrote essays for this periodical containing papers submitted for the annual conjoint meeting of The Frank Waters Society and the Rocky Mountain Modern Language Association.
    - The Carolina Quarterly Vol. 8, No. 1 (1955). (Box 3)
    - Crosscurrents Vol. 4. No. 3 (1984). (Box 3)
    - South Dakota Review Vol. 25, No. 3 (1987). (Box 3)
    - South Dakota Review Vol. 28, No. 1 (1990). (Box 3)
    - South Dakota Review Vol. 33, Nos. 3 & 4 (1995). (Box 3)
    - High Plains Literary Review Vol. 10, No. 2 (1995). (Box 3)
    - Sonora Review Vol. 31 (1996). (Box 3)
    - New Mexico Humanities Review Vol. 5, No. 1 (1982). (Box 3)
    - The Colorado Quarterly Vol. 24, No. 1 (1975). (Box 3)
    - Journal of the Southwest Vol. 30, No. 4 (1988). (Box 3)
    - Western American Literature Vol. 23, No. 2 (1988). (Box 3)
    - Western American Literature Vol. 24, No. 2 (1989). (Box 3)
    - Western American Literature Vol. 29, No. 1 (1994). (Box 3)
    - South Central Review Vol. 6, No. 4 (1989). (Box 3)
    - The Denver Quarterly Vol. 14, No. 2 (1979). (Box 3)
  - Clippings (Box 4)
    - Review of Frank Waters' Of Time & Change in The Bloomsbury Review Vol. 18, No. 5. Sept-Oct 558, and in The Gazette (Colorado Springs), Sept. 6, 1998. (Box 4)
    - Frank Waters. Dictionary of Literary Biography 1986, Includes manuscript and correspondence. (Box 4)
    - William Blackburn. Dictionary of North Carolina Biography. (Box 4)
    - Sight: The Magazine of Psychological Warfare (Box 4)
      Only extant copy of this Army publication edited by A.B.
    - Writers' Forum (1 folder) (Box 4)
    - Waste-Land to Heart-Land: The Quest of Frank Waters in la Tertulia (Southwest Studies, The Colorado College), Vol. 1, No Spring 1985), and in Leviathan (student paper, The Colorado College), Vol. 13, No. 3 (Feb 1987) (Box 4)
    - Review of Robert Fiore's Lazarillo de Tormes in Hispania, Vol. 68, No. 1 (1985). (Box 4)
    - Remarks on the short story today (1994). (Box 4)
    - Reviews in Western American Literature of The Best of the West 2, Vol. 25, No. 4, and of New Writers of the Purple Sage, Vol. '28, No. 3. (Box 4)
    - Secret Research Violates Academic Spirit (Box 4)
    - Letter to the editor of University of Colorado Silver & Gold Record, 1985, Dec. 19 (Box 4)
    - Frank Waters and the Peak of Western Consciousness. Springs Magazine, 1985. (Box 4)
    - Reviews in Cambridge Review, Vol. 81, No. 1979, 7 May 1960. (Box 4)
    - Letter to Taos News, 1996. (Box 4)
  - Writers' Forum, Editorial Files, 1970s-1980s (16 folders) (Box 4)
    Editorial correspondence with writers and other material relevant (especially) to founding the magazine in 1974-75. There are some letters, too, from such well-known writers as Yusef Komunyakaa. See also Box 1.
- Accession (2010-0012), 1880-1998, 15 boxes
  Accession (2010-0012) (6750 items; 9 lin. ft.; dated 1880-1990s) includes writings, drafts, books, and family history materials. Included are materials from Alexander Blackburn's mother, Elizabeth Cheney Blackburn, and the Cheney family.
  - Letters to William Blackburn and Elizabeth Blackburn (parents) when he was at Yale, 1947-1951 (Box 5)
  - Early poems and stories, 2 essays (Box 5)
  - Jane Allison Blackburn (Box 6)
  - Journey to Chile, 1996 (Box 6)
  - Professional correspondence (scholarships, promotions) (Box 6)
  - Letters from well-known people (Box 6)
  - Concerning his cousin Emily's death (Box 6)
  - Letters about his being named (Box 6)
  - Letters, Writer's Forum (Box 6)
  - Harvey Allen family (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
  - Concerning the atomic test and his experience in Nevada, 1951 Oct. 29 (Box 6)
  - Clay Reynolds (Box 6)
  - Angela Davis-Gardner (Box 6)
  - Reviews of Clay Reynolds' novels (Box 6)
  - Gladys Swan (Box 6)
  - Charles Adams (Box 6)
  - Tom Filer (Box 6)
  - James Oliver Brown, literary agent, re first novel (The Cold War of Kitty Pentecost) (Box 7)
  - John Wain (who encouraged ALB's first novel) (Box 7)
  - The Cold War of Kitty Pentecost (Box 7)
  - Writers West books file (Box 7)
  - Draft of Kitty Pentecost (Box 7)
  - Drafts, edits, and correspondence regarding The Golden River and A Little Pain and You Get a Result, 1960s and no date (3 folders) (Box 7)
  - Elementary schoolwork, 1937-1941 (2 folders) (Box 8)
  - High school stories and magazines, 1941-1945 (3 folders) (Box 8)
  - Scrapbook: Alex's baby book (Box 8)
  - A Sunrise Brighter Still (Box 9)
  - Letters, 1984-1985, to and from Charles Adams in reply to ALB's first Waters essay (On Otowi) (Box 9)
  - Frank Waters miscellaneous (Box 9)
  - Benjamin S. Lawson, The Men Who Killed the Deer: Faulkner and Frank Waters, Faulkner Journal Fall 2002/Spring 2003. (Box 9)
  - Frank Waters Foundation (Box 9)
  - The Myth of the Picaro (Box 10)
  - Creative Spirit (Box 10)
  - Tapes and videos, mostly involving presentations on Frank Waters (9 VHS tapes, 23 cassettes) (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous documents: birth certificate, army records, Cambridge University, etc. (Box 12)
  - Vita, commentaries, recognition (Box 12)
  - Essays, reviews, and some activities (Box 12)
  - Reviews, draft essay, miscellaneous (Box 12)
  - Splendor: signings, revisions, commentaries, etc. (Box 13)
  - Suddenly a Mortal Splendor (Box 13)
  - Agents involved with Suddenly a Mortal Splendor (Box 13)
  - Suddenly a Mortal Splendor: early attempts by ALB and Inés B. to find a publisher (Box 13)
  - The Interior Country (Box 14)
  - Higher Elevations (Box 14)
  - Writers' Forum, the early years, 1974-1980s (Box 15)
  - Writers' Forum logo (Box 15)
  - Writers' Forum Volume 21 (Box 15)
  - Craig Lesley (Box 15)
  - Paul Scott Malone (Box 15)
  - Bret Lott (Box 15)
  - Laura Hendrie (former student) (Box 15)
  - Yusef Komunyakaa (former student) (Box 15)
  - Lou Gonzalez Oller (former student) (Box 15)
  - Jill Landem (former student) (Box 15)
  - Michael Petit (Box 15)
  - Elizabeth Blackburn, The Noble Profession (a novel), 1928 (Box 16)
  - Elizabeth Blackburn's manuscripts and publications (3 folders) (Box 16)
  - Photo wallet with Ednah Cheney and her 11 children, 1880s (Box 17)
  - Elizabeth Blackburn's family (Box 17)
  - Letters, 1925-1942 (Box 17)
  - Letters from James M. Cain (Box 17)
  - Letters concerning H. Phelps Putnam (Box 17)
  - Letters, Donald Ogden Stewart, 1921 (Box 17)
  - Cheney family trees (Box 17)
  - Letters from Elizabeth Blackburn to Alexander Blackburn at Yale, 1947-1951 (Box 18)
  - Letters from Elizabeth Blackburn to Alexander Blackburn, 1952-1980 (Box 18)
  - Books (Box 19)
    - If All Great Men, by Margreta Swenson Cheney (Box 19)
    - Paintings, by Russell Cheney (Box 19)
    - Parents and Children: A Family Vignette, by Antoinette Cheney Crocker (Box 19)
    - Writers' Forum, Volume 25, 1999 (Box 19)
    - The Bridge of San Luis Rey, by Thornton Wilder (Box 19)
    - Blue Notes: Essays, Interviews, and Commentaries, by Yusef Komunyakaa (Box 19)
    - Neurosis and Human Growth: The Struggle Toward Self-Realization, by Karen Horney, M.D. (Box 19)
    - Sarah Orne Jewett, by Francis Otto Matthiessen (Box 19)
    - Sites of Insight: A Guide to Colorado Sacred Places, edited by James Lough (Box 19)
    - War, Literature, & The Arts, Volume 15, Numbers 1-2 (Box 19)
    - A Selected, Annotated Bibliography of Books about Taos and New Mexico, by Arthur J. Bachrach (Box 19)
    - Tributes to Frank Waters, by T.N. Luther (Box 19)
    - Books from T.N. Luther (Box 19)
    - A Few Reminscences of my Exeter Life, by Elizabeth Dow Leonard (Box 19)
    - How to Stay Married, by Norman M. Lobsenz and Clark W. Blackburn (Box 19)
    - By a Stroke of Luck! An Autobiography, by Donald Ogden Stewart (Box 19)
    - The Abnormal Personality, by Robert W. White, Ph.D. (Box 19)
    - The Neurotic Personality of Our Time, by Karen Horney, M.D. (Box 19)
    - Journals, 1799-1805, Mary B. Howell (Box 20)
    - Cheney Hall (Box 20)
    - Studies in Frank Waters-XXII (Box 20)
    - Studies in Frank Waters-XX (Box 20)
    - Studies in Frank Waters-XI (Box 20)
    - Frank Waters and Charles: Eighty Years of Memories with a Friend, by Charles Elbert Hathaway (Box 20)
    - Some Memories of the K.Ds. An Old Fashioned Family, by Helen Cheney Bayne (Box 20)
    - Meeting the Professor: Growing up in the William Blackburn Family, by Alexander Blackburn (Box 20)
    - Collected Poems of Harvey Allen, edited by Alexander Blackburn (Box 20)
    - Monographie de la Cathedrale de Chartres (Box 20)
    - Outline Sketches of the Lives of Six Generations of Cheneys with some Letters, by Helen Cheney Bayne (Box 20)
    - Life in New Orleans 1870-1898 (Box 20)
    - Life in New York 1898-1917 (Box 20)
    - Life in Paris 1919-1928 (Box 20)
- Accession (2020-0099), 1930s-2020
  Scope and Contents
  Includes writings, drafts, books, and family history materials. A more detailed inventory of the boxes is included in Acc 2020/99: Box 1.
  - Writings by Blackburn, detailed inventory of Acc. 2020-0099, 1977-2020 (Box Acc 2020/99: Box 1)
    The typed inventory was provided by Blackburn and may not match the current box numbers. Researchers will need to consult materials to confirm inventory. This box also includes books Blackburn wrote, edited, or to which Blackburn contributed. Titles are: "The Fire Within"; "The Myth of the Picaro"; "Meeting the Professor"; "Gifts from the Heart"; "The Cold War of Kitty Pentecost"; "Suddenly a Mortal Splendor"; "The Voice of the Children in the Apple Tree"; "The Door of the Sad People"; "Pure Waters: Frank Waters and the Quest for the Cosmic"; "Great Oaks: Memoirs of the Cheney Family"; "Old Manchester"; "Age of Atoms"; "The Emergence of Frank Waters".
  - Published essays and stories by Blackburn and Inés Dolz-Blackburn, 1997-2017 (Box Acc 2020/99: Box 2)
  - Essays, letters, clippings, photographs, family history (Box Acc 2020/99: Box 3)
  - Correspondence, clippings, awards, writings, and photographs relating to Blackburn's education and career, 1946-2019 (Box Acc 2020/99: Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1985-2020 (Box Acc 2020/99: Box 5)
    Inlcudes clippings and photographs; printout of Blackburn's website; sketchbook; tributes to Blackburn.
  - Nominations and awards, reviews, correspondence, 1994-2015 (Box Acc 2020/99: Box 6)
  - Correspondence with John Nizalowski about the publication of "The Emergence of Frank Waters" (Box Acc 2020/99: Box 7)
  - Correspondence with Clay Reynolds (Box Acc 2020/99: Box 8)
  - Correspondence (Box Acc 2020/99: Box 9)
    Correspondents include: Myrial A. Holbrook; Joanne Greenberg; Rudolfo A. Anaya; David Blackburn; Philip Blackburn; Rufus Phillips; Phaedra Greenwood; William deBuys; Angela Davis-Gardner; John Nichols; Leigh Cross; Jeffrey Putnam; Gladys Swan; Betsy Packard; George Blackburn, Jr.; Waring Blackburn; Lawrence Gustafson; Joan Mellon; and Emily Haskett (for Alan Polsky).
  - Correspondence, awards, biographical materials (Box Acc 2020/99: Box 10)
    Includes materials relating to Alexander Blackburn and other family members including William Blackburn, Elizabeth Cheney Blackburn, and Roma Blackburn.
  - Course materials about Frank Waters (Box Acc 2020/99: Box 11)
    Materials relating to course on Waters; Faculty course questionaires; evaluations of Blackburn's teaching at UCCS.
  - Course materials about western literature (Box Acc 2020/99: Box 12)
  - Source materials for "Meeting the Professor" (Box Acc 2020/99: Box 13)
  - "Gifts from the Heart" clippings, reviews, award information (Box Acc 2020/99: Box 14)
  - "The Door of the Sad People" sources, workshetes, queries (Box Acc 2020/99: Box 15)
  - "The Door of the Sad People" research materials (Box Acc 2020/99: Box 16)
  - "The Voice of the Children in the Apple Tree" research materials (Box Acc 2020/99: Box 17)
  - "Suddenly a Mortal Splendor" sources and reviews (Box Acc 2020/99: Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous notes and correspondence (Box Acc 2020/99: Box 19)
    Includes correspondence with Yusef Komunyakaa and John Nizalowski; a notebook on Harvey Allen's poetry; and a typescript of Remembering Time.
  - "The Emergence of Frank Waters" draft, 2020 (Box Acc 2020/99: Box 20)